<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<aiml>
    
     <!--  Every yes and No patterns can be written in same catagory using <condition> tag to reduce the lines of code -->
     
      <!-- use <srai> tag for recursion (i.e.like a loop) to reduce size ot the code -->
      
      <!-- Better to avoid (not mandatory) using <sari> tag to pass to a pattern having <that> tag to  -->
      
      <!-- use <br> tag for new line  -->
    
   <category>
      <pattern> # headache # </pattern><template>Ok.Let me help you with your hedache. Please answer the following questions.<think><set name = "topic">headache</set></think></template>  
   </category>
   
   <topic name = "headache">
      <category>
               <pattern> # ok # </pattern><template>How long has this been troubling you
               1)Less than one day
               2)One day to one week
               3)More than one week)
               Enter the serial number :</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># hmm #</pattern><template><srai># ok #</srai>.</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>*</pattern><template>Please enter a valid input </template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 3 #</pattern><template><srai># 2 #</srai>.</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 2 #</pattern><template>How would you describe the intensity of your headache (mild,moderate,severe)</template>
      </category> 
      
      <category>
               <pattern>severe</pattern><that>_ intensity *</that><template>Do you have nausea or vomiting (Yes/No) ?</template>
      </category> 
      
      <category>
               <pattern>mild</pattern><that>_ intensity *</that><template>is the pain on one or both sides of the head?</template>
      </category> 
      
      <category>
               <pattern>moderate</pattern><that>_ intensity *</that><template>is the pain on one or both sides of the head?</template>
      </category> 
      
      <category>
               <pattern>*</pattern><that>_ sides *</that><template>Ok. Do you also have atleast two or more of the following symptoms: Facial pain or pressure"Stuffed-up" noseRunny noseLoss of smellCough or congestionFeverBad breathFatigueDental pain(Yes/NO) ?</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>Yes</pattern><that>_ atleast two or more *</that><template>It may be Acute Sinusitis.Some of the primary medication that you can take care are <srai>1111111111</srai> </template>
      </category>
     
     <!-- infinite loop . only exits when exit is entered -->
     
      <category>
               <pattern>1111111111</pattern><template>
	       1)Saline nasal spray
               2)Nasal corticosteroids.
               3)Decongestants.
               4)OTC pain relievers.
               5)Antibiotics.
               6)Immunotherapy.
               To know about Acute Sinusitis primary medications briefly enter their serial number or type "exit" (without votes) to move out from primary medications of Acute Sinusitis :</template>
      </category>
               
      <category>
               <pattern># 1 #</pattern><that>_ Acute Sinusitis primary medications *</that><template>Saline nasal spray :- which you spray into your nose several times a day to rinse your nasal passages.<srai>1111111111</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 2 #</pattern><that>_ Acute Sinusitis primary medications *</that><template>Nasal corticosteroids :- These nasal sprays help prevent and treat inflammation. Examples include fluticasone (Flonase Allergy Relief, Flonase Sensimist Allergy Relief, others), budesonide (Rhinocort Allergy), mometasone (Nasonex) and beclomethasone (Beconase AQ, Qnasl, others).<srai>1111111111</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 3 #</pattern><that>_ Acute Sinusitis primary medications *</that><template>Decongestants :- These medications are available in over-the-counter (OTC) and prescription liquids, tablets and nasal sprays. Use nasal decongestants for only a few days. Otherwise they may cause the return of more-severe congestion (rebound congestion).<srai>1111111111</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 4 #</pattern><that>_ Acute Sinusitis primary medications *</that><template>OTC pain relievers :- OTC pain relievers such as acetaminophen (Tylenol, others), ibuprofen (Advil, Motrin IB, others) or aspirin.Use caution when giving aspirin to children or teenagers. Children and teenagers recovering from chickenpox or flu-like symptoms should never take aspirin. This is because aspirin has been linked to Reye's syndrome, a rare but potentially life-threatening condition, in such children.<srai>1111111111</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 5 #</pattern><that>_ Acute Sinusitis primary medications *</that><template>Antibiotics :- Antibiotics usually aren't needed to treat acute sinusitis. Even if your acute sinusitis is bacterial, it may clear up without treatment. Your doctor might wait and watch to see if your acute sinusitis worsens before prescribing antibiotics.However, severe, progressive or persistent symptoms might require antibiotics. If your doctor prescribes an antibiotic, be sure to take the whole course, even after your symptoms get better. If you stop taking them early, your symptoms may recur.<srai>1111111111</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 6 #</pattern><that>_ Acute Sinusitis primary medications *</that><template>Immunotherapy :- If allergies are contributing to your sinusitis, allergy shots (immunotherapy) that help reduce the body's reaction to specific allergens may help treat your symptoms.<srai>1111111111</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>No</pattern><that>_ atleast two or more *</that><template>Do you have nausea or vomiting (Yes/No) ?</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>Yes</pattern><that>_ nausea *</that><template>Is it severe enough to interfere with routine activities (Yes/No) ?</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>No</pattern><that>_ nausea *</that><template>Do you have a feeling of congestion or fullness in your face (Yes/No) ?</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>Yes</pattern><that>_ congestion or fullness *</that><template>Do you have nasal obstruction or nasal blockage (Yes/No) ?</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>No</pattern><that>_ congestion or fullness *</that><template>It might be a serious problem .Consult to a doctor as soon as possible.<srai>exit</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>No</pattern><that>_ nasal obstruction *</that><template>It might be a serious problem .Consult to a doctor as soon as possible.<srai>exit</srai></template>
      </category>
      
       <category>
               <pattern>Yes</pattern><that>_ nasal obstruction *</that><template>It may be Chronic Sinusitis.Some of the primary medication that you can take care are <srai>4444444444</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <!-- infinite loop . only exits when exit is entered -->
      
      <category>
               <pattern>4444444444</pattern><template>
	       1)Saline nasal irrigation
               2)Nasal corticosteroids.
               3)Oral or injected corticosteroids.
               4)Aspirin desensitization treatment
               5)Antibiotics.
               6)Immunotherapy.
               To know about Chronic Sinusitis primary medications briefly enter their serial number or type "exit" (without votes) to move out from primary medications of Acute Sinusitis :</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 1 #</pattern><that>_ Chronic Sinusitis primary medications *</that><template>Saline nasal irrigation :- with nasal sprays or solutions, reduces drainage and rinses away irritants and allergies.<srai>4444444444</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 2 #</pattern><that>_ Chronic Sinusitis primary medications *</that><template>Nasal corticosteroids :- These nasal sprays help prevent and treat inflammation. Examples include fluticasone, triamcinolone, budesonide, mometasone and beclomethasone. If the sprays aren't effective enough, your doctor might recommend rinsing with a solution of saline mixed with drops of budesonide or using a nasal mist of the solution.<srai>4444444444</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 3 #</pattern><that>_ Chronic Sinusitis primary medications *</that><template>Oral or injected corticosteroids :- These medications are used to relieve inflammation from severe sinusitis, especially if you also have nasal polyps. Oral corticosteroids can cause serious side effects when used long term, so they're used only to treat severe symptoms.<srai>4444444444</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 4 #</pattern><that>_ Chronic Sinusitis primary medications *</that><template>Aspirin desensitization treatment :- if you have reactions to aspirin that cause sinusitis. Under medical supervision, you're gradually given larger doses of aspirin to increase your tolerance.<srai>4444444444</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 5 #</pattern><that>_ Chronic Sinusitis primary medications *</that><template>Antibiotics :- Antibiotics are sometimes necessary for sinusitis if you have a bacterial infection. If your doctor can't rule out an underlying infection, he or she might recommend an antibiotic, sometimes with other medications.<srai>4444444444</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 6 #</pattern><that>_ Chronic Sinusitis primary medications *</that><template>Immunotherapy :- If allergies are contributing to your sinusitis, allergy shots (immunotherapy) that help reduce the body's reaction to specific allergens might improve the condition.<srai>4444444444</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>No</pattern><that>_  with routine *</that><template>Do you have a feeling of squeezing or pressure (Yes/No) ?</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>Yes</pattern><that>_ squeezing *</that><template>It may be tension-type headache.Some of the primary medication that you can take care are <srai>3333333333</srai> </template>
      </category>
      
      <!-- infinite loop . only exits when exit is entered -->
      
      <category>
               <pattern>3333333333</pattern><template>
	       1)Pain relievers.
               2)Combination medications.
               3)Triptans and narcotics.
               4)Some general medications.
               To know about tension-type headache primary medications briefly enter their serial number or type "exit" (without votes) to move out from primary medications of tension-type headache :</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 1 #</pattern><that>_ tension-type headache primary medications *</that><template>Pain relievers :- Simple OTC pain relievers are usually the first line of treatment for reducing headache pain. These include the drugs aspirin, ibuprofen (Advil, Motrin IB, others) and naproxen (Aleve).Prescription medications include naproxen (Naprosyn), indomethacin (Indocin) and ketorolac (Ketorolac Tromethamine).<srai>3333333333</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 2 #</pattern><that>_ tension-type headache primary medications *</that><template>Combination medications :- Aspirin or acetaminophen or both are often combined with caffeine or a sedative drug in a single medication. Combination drugs may be more effective than are single-ingredient pain relievers. Many combination drugs are available OTC.<srai>3333333333</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 3 #</pattern><that>_ tension-type headache primary medications *</that><template>Triptans and narcotics :- For people who experience both migraines and episodic tension headaches, a triptan can effectively relieve the pain of both headaches. Opiates, or narcotics, are rarely used because of their side effects and potential for dependency.<srai>3333333333</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 4 #</pattern><that>_ tension-type headache primary medications *</that><template>Some general medications :- 
	       1)Ice pack held over the eyes or forehead
               2)Heating pad set on low or hot shower to relax tense neck and shoulder muscles
               3)Sleep, or at least resting in a dark room
               4)Taking breaks from stressful situations
               5)Regular exercise to increase endorphin levels and relax muscles. Even if you already have a headache, exercising may relieve the pain. However, intense exercise may bring on a headache.<srai>3333333333</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>No</pattern><that>_ squeezing *</that><template>It might be a serious problem .Consult to a doctor as soon as possible.<srai>exit</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>Yes</pattern><that>_ severe *</that><template>Does it lasts for several hours (Yes/No) ?</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>No</pattern><that>_ severe *</that><template>It might be a serious problem .Consult to a doctor as soon as possible.<srai>exit</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>Yes</pattern><that>_ lasts for several *</that><template>It might be a Migraine.Some of the primary medication that you can take care are <srai>2222222222</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <!-- infinite loop . only exits when exit is entered -->
      
      <category>
               <pattern>2222222222</pattern><template>
 	       1)Pain relievers.
               2)Triptans.
               3)Dihydroergotamines (D.H.E. 45, Migranal).
               4)Lasmiditan (Reyvow).
               5)Ubrogepant (Ubrelvy).
               6)Opioid medications.
               7)Anti-nausea drugs.
               To know about Migraine primary medications briefly enter their serial number or type "exit" (without votes) to move out from primary medications of Migraine :</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 1 #</pattern><that>_ Migraine primary medications *</that><template>Pain relievers :- These over-the-counter or prescription pain relievers include aspirin or ibuprofen (Advil, Motrin IB, others). When taken too long, these might cause medication-overuse headaches, and possibly ulcers and bleeding in the gastrointestinal tract.Migraine relief medications that combine caffeine, aspirin and acetaminophen (Excedrin Migraine) may be helpful, but usually only against mild migraine pain.<srai>2222222222</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 2 #</pattern><that>_ Migraine primary medications *</that><template>Triptans :- These are prescription drugs such as sumatriptan (Imitrex, Tosymra) and rizatriptan (Maxalt) are prescription drugs used for migraine because they block pain pathways in the brain. Taken as pills, shots or nasal sprays, they can relieve many symptoms of migraine. They might not be safe for those at risk of a stroke or heart attack.<srai>2222222222</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 3 #</pattern><that>_ Migraine primary medications *</that><template>Dihydroergotamines (D.H.E. 45, Migranal) :- Available as a nasal spray or injection, these are most effective when taken shortly after the start of migraine symptoms for migraines that tend to last longer than 24 hours. Side effects can include worsening of migraine-related vomiting and nausea.People with coronary artery disease, high blood pressure, or kidney or liver disease should avoid dihydrogergotamines.<srai>2222222222</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 4 #</pattern><that>_ Migraine primary medications *</that><template>Lasmiditan (Reyvow) :- This new oral tablet is approved for the treatment of migraine with or without aura. In drug trials, lasmiditan significantly improved pain as well as nausea and sensitivity to light and sound. Lasmiditan can have a sedative effect and cause dizziness, so people taking it are advised not to drive or operate machinery for at least eight hours. Lasmiditan also shouldn't be taken with alcohol or other drugs that depress the central nervous system.<srai>2222222222</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 5 #</pattern><that>_ Migraine primary medications *</that><template>Ubrogepant (Ubrelvy) :- This oral calcitonin gene-related peptide receptor antagonist is approved for the treatment of acute migraine with or without aura in adults. It's the first drug of this type approved for migraine treatment. In drug trials, ubrogepant was more effective than placebo in relieving pain and other migraine symptoms such as nausea and sensitivity to light and sound two hours after taking it. Common side effects include dry mouth, nausea and excessive sleepiness. Ubrogepant should not be taken with strong CYP3A4 inhibitor drugs.However, severe, progressive or persistent symptoms might require antibiotics. If your doctor prescribes an antibiotic, be sure to take the whole course, even after your symptoms get better. If you stop taking them early, your symptoms may recur.<srai>2222222222</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 6 #</pattern><that>_ Migraine primary medications *</that><template>Opioid medications :- People who have migraines who can't take other migraine medications, narcotic opioid medications, especially those that contain codeine, might help. Because they can be highly addictive, these are usually used only if no other treatments are effective.<srai>2222222222</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 7 #</pattern><that>_ Migraine primary medications *</that><template>Anti-nausea drugs :- These can help if your migraine with aura is accompanied by nausea and vomiting. Anti-nausea drugs include chlorpromazine, metoclopramide (Reglan) or prochlorperazine (Compro). These are usually taken with pain medications.<srai>2222222222</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 1 #</pattern><template>Have you taken any medicine so far (Yes/No) ?</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># Yes #</pattern><that>_ taken any medicine *</that><template><srai>2</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># no #</pattern><that>_ taken any medicine *</that><template>It might be due to stress or less sleep or tension.Take paracetamol or any similar medicine and rest.If the pain still continue come back to us.<srai>exit</srai></template>
      </category>
      
       <!-- All the conversation convergs to here for ending i.e. after any conversion user enters this block to exit  -->
      
      <category>
               <pattern>exit</pattern><template>Do you want to know medications for prevention headache or the diseases releated to Headache (Yes/No) ?</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>Yes</pattern><that>_ medications for prevention *</that><template>Please Enter the serial number to know briefly about the prevention medications of the corresponding disease.<srai>5555555555</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <!-- infinite loop . only exits when exit is entered -->
      
      <category>
               <pattern>5555555555</pattern><template>
	       1)Headache.
               2)Migraine.
               3)Chronic Sinusitis.
               4)Some generel medications.
               To know about prevention medications briefly enter their serial number or type "Bye" (without votes) to exit :</template>
      </category>
      
      <!-- you can use <random>,<li> tags if you want to give a single medication at a time -->
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 1 #</pattern><that>_ prevention medications *</that><template>Prevention medications for headache :
               1)Be aware of early symptoms so you can try to stop the headache as soon as it begins.
               2)Don’t smoke, and if you do, quit.
               3)Don’t skip meals.
               4)Cut down on caffeine and alcohol (reduce caffeine intake gradually because withdrawal may cause headaches).
               5)top all over-the-counter medicines and herbal remedies.
               6)Maintain a regular eating and sleeping schedule.
               7)Exercise regularly.
               8)Incorporate relaxation activities into your daily routine, such as meditation, yoga, stretching exercises, and massage
               9)Improve your posture, possibly by adjusting your workstation.<srai>5555555555</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 2 #</pattern><that>_ prevention medications *</that><template>Prevention medications for Migraine.
               1)Blood pressure-lowering medications. These include beta blockers such as propranolol (Inderal, Innopran XL, others) and metoprolol tartrate (Lopressor). Calcium channel blockers such as verapamil (Tarka, Verelan) can be helpful in preventing migraines with aura.
               2)Antidepressants. A tricyclic antidepressant (amitriptyline) can prevent migraines. Because of the side effects of amitriptyline, such as sleepiness and weight gain, other antidepressants might be prescribed instead.
               3)Anti-seizure drugs. Valproate and topiramate (Topamax) might help you have less frequent migraines, but can cause side effects such as dizziness, weight changes, nausea and more.
               4)Botox injections. Injections of onabotulinumtoxinA (Botox) about every 12 weeks help prevent migraines in some adults.
               5)Calcitonin gene-related peptide (CGRP) monoclonal antibodies. Erenumab-aooe (Aimovig), fremanezumab-vfrm (Ajovy) and galcanezumab-gnlm (Emgality) are newer drugs approved by the Food and Drug Administration to treat migraines. They're given monthly by injection. The most common side effect is a reaction at the injection site.<srai>5555555555</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 3 #</pattern><that>_ prevention medications *</that><template>prevention medications for Acute sinusitis :
               1)Humidify. Use a humidifier in rooms where you spend a lot of time. Follow the instructions for regular cleaning.
               2)Drink lots of fluids. They'll help thin the mucus, which reduces the blockage in your sinuses. Cut down on alcohol, which makes the swelling worse.
               3)Rest. When you've got a sinus infection, take it easier than normal. Get plenty of sleep and give your body a chance to recover.
               4)Use warm heat. Put a warm, wet towel on your face. It can take off some of the pressure.<srai>5555555555</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># 4 #</pattern><that>_ prevention medications *</that><template>Some general medications :-
               1)Ice pack held over the eyes or forehead
               2)Heating pad set on low or hot shower to relax tense neck and shoulder muscles
               3)Sleep, or at least resting in a dark room
               4)Taking breaks from stressful situations
               5)Regular exercise to increase endorphin levels and relax muscles. Even if you already have a headache, exercising may relieve the pain. However, intense exercise may bring on a headache.<srai>5555555555</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># Bye #</pattern><that>_ prevention medications *</that><template>Ok Bye, take care of your health. You can contact us when ever needed </template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern># No #</pattern><that>_ medications for prevention *</that><template>Ok. Bye, take care of your health. You can contact us when ever needed </template>
      </category>
      
   </topic>
   
</aiml>
