<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<aiml>
    
   <category>
      <pattern> # Stomach pain # </pattern><template>Ok.Let me help you with your Stomach pain. Please answer the following questions.<think><set name = "topic">Stomach pain</set></think></template>  
   </category>
   
   <topic name = "Stomach pain">
      <category>
               <pattern> # ok # </pattern>
               <template>How long has this been troubling you  
                                                       1.Less than one day 
                                                       2.One day to one week 
                                                       3.One week to one month 
                                                       4.More than one month.... Select any number:</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>4</pattern><template>It might be a severe problem .Consult to a doctor as soon as possible.</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>2</pattern><template>How would you describe the intensity of your Stomach pain (mild,moderate,severe)</template>
      </category> 
      
      <category>
               <pattern>3</pattern><template><srai>2</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>1</pattern><template><srai>2</srai></template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>severe</pattern><that>_ intensity *</that><template><srai>4</srai></template>
      </category> 
      
      <category>
               <pattern>mild</pattern><that>_ intensity *</that><template>It's not a big problem jst take loperamide (Imodium) or bismuth subsalicylate (Kaopectate or Pepto-Bismol) :)</template>
      </category> 
      
      <category>
               <pattern>moderate</pattern><that>_ intensity *</that><template>Where is the pain located within the abdomen
                                                                              1.All over the abdomen 
                                                                              2.In the specific part of abdomen..</template>
      </category> 
      
      <category>
               <pattern>1</pattern><that>_ located *</that><template>Do you also have atleast one among the following symptoms: Diarrhoea Do your stools looser than usual (Yes/NO) </template>
      </category>
      
       <category>
              <pattern>Yes</pattern><that>_ atleast one among *</that><template>Does the diarrhoea seems to be extremly watery(Yes or NO)</template>
      
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>Yes</pattern><that>_ watery *</that><template>Does the diarrhoea contains blood(Yes/No)</template>
              
      </category>
      
       <category>
               <pattern>NO</pattern><that> _ watery *</that><template><srai>Yes</srai></template>
      </category>

     <category>
             <pattern>Yes</pattern><that> _ blood * </that><template> This are symptoms for dysentery caused by bacterial infection... you will be probably start with a 10-day course of an antimicrobial medication, such as Flagyl (metronidazole). Diloxanide furoate, paromomycin , or iodoquinol, depending on the severity of symptoms..SO IT IS BETTER TO CONSULT A DOCTOR!!</template>
     </category>
     
      <category>
               <pattern>NO</pattern><that>_ blood *</that><template>This are symptoms for normal diarrhoea take some drugs which  include (codeine phosphate, co-phenotrope, loperamide, and kaolin and morphine mixture)</template>
      </category>
     
     <category>
             <pattern>Yes</pattern><that></that>
     </category>
     
       <category>
               <pattern>2</pattern><that>_ located *</that><template>Please select position of pain   
                                                                     1.Area above the stomach or Upper right side or Upper left side or Lower right side or Around the belly button 
                                                                     2.Lower left side 
                                                                     3.In the pelvic region .. </template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
              <pattern>1</pattern><that> _ of pain *</that><template> Do you have any other Symptoms like 
                                                                                 =>Abdominal pain migration 
                                                                                 =>Sharp pain 
                                                                                 =>Mild-Abdominal pain(Yes/No) </template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
               <pattern>Yes</pattern><that> _ other Symptoms like * </that><template>This are symptoms for appendix..Consult a doctor as soon as possible!!</template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
            <pattern>no</pattern><that>_ other Symptoms like *</that><template>If you feel any inflammation these are symptoms for Gastritis so take  these drugs include the prescription and over-the-counter medications Taking antacids and other drugs (such as proton pump inhibitors or H-2 blockers) to reduce stomach acid. 
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  Avoiding hot and spicy foods. 
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  For gastritis caused by H. ...                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              If the gastritis is caused by pernicious anemia, B12 vitamin shots will be given. </template>
      </category>
      
      <category>
             <pattern>2</pattern><that>_ of pain *</that><template>These are symptoms of diverticulitis..treated using diet modifications, antibiotics, and possibly surgery. Mild diverticulitis infection may be treated with bed rest, stool softeners, a liquid diet, antibiotics to fight the infection, and possibly antispasmodic drugs.</template>
      </category>
      
     <category>
              <pattern>3</pattern><that>_ of pain *</that><template>Pelvic pain affects the lowest part of the abdomen, between the belly button and groin. In women, pelvic pain may be a sign of menstrual cramps, ovulation, or a gastrointestinal issue such as a food intolerance. It can also develop due to a more serious problem. ... When this is the case, a woman may need to see a doctor.Or for  lil pain you can take Take over-the-counter pain medicine like ibuprofen (Advil), naproxen (Aleve), or acetaminophen (Tylenol). ... 
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               Exercise. 
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               Take rest 
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               heating pad on your belly or lower back. 
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               Take a hot bath.</template>
     </category> 
     <category>
           <pattern>no</pattern><that>_ atleast one among *</that><template>This is just a normal pain take acetaminophen (Aspirin Free Anacin, Liquiprin, Panadol, Tylenol) might be helpful. But stay away from non-steroidal anti-inflammatories (NSAIDs) like aspirin, ibuprofen (Advil, Midol, Motrin), or naproxen (Naprosyn, Aleve, Anaprox, Naprelan). They can irritate your stomach.Consult doctor if you dont feel well even after taking those medicine.. </template>
     </category>
      
   </topic>
   
</aiml>
